(Sings)
(تُغنّي)
Water
ماء
Boy
فتي
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
where are you hidin'?
أين تختبئ؟
If you don't come right here,
إذا لم تأتي إلى هنا،
I'm gonna tell
سأخبر
your pa on you.
والدك عنك.
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
There ain't no hammer --
لا يوجد مطرقة
that's on this mountain
علي هذا الجبل
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
That ring like mine, boy --
فهذا الرنين مثل رنيني يا فتى
that ring like mine.
هذا الرنين مثل رنيني.
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
I'm gonna bust this rock, boy --
سأُحطم هذه الصخرة يا فتى
from here to Macon.
من هنا إلى ماكون.
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
All the way to the jail, boy --
علي طول الطريق إلي السجن يا فتي
all the way to the jail.
علي طول الطريق إلي السجن.
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
You jack of diamonds --
أنت الولد في ورق اللعب
(Music)
(موسيقى)
I know you of old boy,
أعرفك بالفتى العجوز،
I know you of old.
أعرفك بالعجوز.
You done robbed my pocket,
لقد سرقت جيبي،
of silver and gold, boy,
من الفضة والذهب يا فتى
of silver and gold.
من الفضة والذهب.
Water Boy,
فتى الماء،
where are you hidin'?
أين تختبئ؟
If you don't come right here,
إن لم تأتي إلى هنا،
I'm gonna tell your pa on you.
سأخبر والدك عنك.
There ain't no hammer
ليس هناك مطرقة
that's on this mountain
على هذا الجبل
that ring like mine, boy,
وهذا الرنين مثل رنيني يا فتى،
that ring like mine.
هذا الرنين مثل رنيني.
I'm gonna bust this rock, boy,
سأحطم هذه الصخرة يا فتى
from here to Macon.
من هنا إلي ماكون
All the way to the jail, boy,
على طول الطريق إلي السجن يا فتى،
all the way to the jail.
على طول الطريق إلى السجن.
Water
ماء
Boy
فتى
(Guitar strum)
(عزف على الغيتار)
where are you hidin'?
أين تختبئ؟
If you don't come right here,
إن لم تأتي هنا الآن،
I'm gonna tell
سأخبر
your pa
والدك
on you.
عنك.
(Guitar strum)
(العزف علي الغيتار)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
That was a song based on numerous work songs,
كانت تلك أغنية مُرتكزة على العديد من الأغاني،
and it was arranged by Odetta,
ولقد نسّقت بواسطة أوديتا،
a hero of mine.
وهو بطلٌ لي.
And this next song, well,
حسناً، وفي الأغنية التالية،
I do a lot of historical music,
أقوم بالعديد من الموسيقى التاريخية،
starting with the Carolina Chocolate Drops
بدءاً من كارولينا قطرات الشيكولاتة
and continuing on in my solo endeavors.
استمراراً فى جهودي المنفردة.
And I believe that knowing your history as a musician
وأعتقد أن معرفة تاريخك كموسيقي
is super important --
هو أمر مهم جداً
it's important as a person,
إنه مهم كشخص،
it's important as a country,
إنه مهم كبلد،
it's important as a people.
وإنه مهم كشعب.
So I read a lot about where the music comes from
لذا أقرأ كثيراً من أين تأتي الموسيقى
and where this country comes from.
ومن أين يأتى هذا البلد.
I've been reading a lot about the Civil War
وكنت أقرأ كثيراً عن الحروب الأهلية
and about slavery.
وعن الرق.
And it's really tough.
وهي قاسية حقاً.
You know?
هل تعرف؟
It's really tough reading.
إنها قراءةٌ قاسيةٌ حقاً.
And so as an artist, what I do with all that emotion,
وبوصفي فنانة، ما أفعله مع كل تلك المشاعر،
reading these people's stories,
قراءة قصص هؤلاء الناس،
not just, "Oh, slavery was terrible."
لا أقول فقط: "آه، كانت العبودية فظيعة."
Yes, it was.
نعم، كانت كذلك.
But it's reading individual narratives of how it was for these people.
ولكنها قراءة الروايات الفردية لكيف كان الأمر لهؤلاء الناس.
You know?
هل تعرف؟
Then it's like, "Yeah, that could've been me."
ثم إنها مثل "نعم، ويمكن أن أكون أنا".
And it is people now. You know?
ويتعلق الأمر بالناس الآن. أتعلمون؟
So what you do with all that emotion
ولذلك، فماذا تفعل مع كل تلك العاطفة
is you've got to do something with it.
فعليك أن تفعل شيئاً معها.
As an artist, I write.
وكفنانة أكتب.
So I wrote a song based on some of those narratives that I read,
فكتبت أغنية على أساس بعض من تلك الروايات التى قرأت،
and it's called, "Come Love Come."
وتسمي " تعال أيها الحب تعال."
We're going to do it for you now.
والآن، سنغنيها لكم.
(Claps)
(تصفيق)
(Sings) Come love come,
(تغني) تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً،
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً،
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Sings) When I was four,
(تغني) عندما كنت في الرابعة،
my loving mam was cornered by the boss's man.
كان الرئيس يحاصر أمي العزيزة.
She turned her head and got struck down,
أحنت رأسها وطُرحت أرضاً،
they buried her in the cold, cold ground.
ودفنوها في البرد، في أرض باردة.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي،
(Music)
(موسيقى).
When I was 12,
عندما بلغت الثانية عشر،
my father dear
كان والدي العزيز
was strong of arm and free of fear
قوي الذراع ولا يخاف
until the day he raised his hand,
إلى اليوم الذي رفع فيه يدُه،
then he was sold to Alabama.
ثُم بِيع إلى ألاباما.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً،
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي،
(Music)
(موسيقى)
When I was 16, found my bloom
وعندما كنت في السادسة عشر، وجدت ازدهاري
and found my man,
ووجدت رجُلي،
we jumped the broom.
فقفزنا على المركب.
We pledged each other the rest of our lives
وتعهدنا لبعضنا البعض ببقية حياتنا
and on Saturday nights we were man and wife.
وكنا الرجل والزوجة في ليالي السبت.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً،
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
When I was 18,
وعندما كنت في الثامنة عشر،
bugles called
إستُدعت الأبواق
and boys in blue came o'er the wall.
وجاء البنين يرتدون الأزرق من وراء الجدار.
I took my chance and followed free,
فأخذت فرصتي وأتبعتهُم بحرية،
they led the way to Tennessee.
وسلكوا الطريق إلى تينيسي.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Now here I sit in a tiny shack
وهنا أجلس الآن فى كوخ صغير
with 13 others at my back.
مع ثلاثة عشر آخرين من خلفي.
I've sent you word,
ولقد أرسلت لك كلمة،
so all I can do
لذا كلّ ما بوسعي عمله
is wait and wait and wait and wait
هو أن أنتظر وأنتظر وأنتظر وأنتظر
and wait
وأنتظر
and wait for you.
وأنتظرك.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies low,
الطريق يكمن منخفضاً
the way is long and hard, I know.
وأنا أعرف أنه طويل وشاق.
Come love come,
تعال أيها الحب تعال،
the road lies free,
الطريق يكمن حُراً
I'll wait for you in Tennessee.
سأنتظرك في تينيسي.
Oh,
أوه
oh.
أوه،
Whoa ... oh I'll wait for you.
ووه ... أوه سأنتظرك.
I'll wait for you.
سأنتظرك.
I'll wait for you
سأنتظرك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
So, with the dark you have to have the light.
لذا، يجب أن يكون لديك ضوء مع الظلام.
And in the African-American community,
وفي المجتمع الإفريقي الأمريكي،
it's been the work of many hundreds of years
لقد كان العمل لعدة مئات من السنين
to find a way to lift ourselves up.
لإيجاد وسيلة للنهوض بأنفسنا.
So I'm going to end with a couple of tunes from Sister Rosetta Tharpe,
ولذلك، سأختم مع اثنين من الألحان من الأخت روزيتا ثارب،
one of the more influential American music figures
واحدة من الشخصيات الموسيقية الأمريكية الأكثر تأثيراً
that most of you probably never heard of.
ومن المحتمل أن معظمكم لم يسمع بها.
If you have, I'm so happy.
إن كنتم سمعتم بها، فأنا سعيدة جداً.
She's one of the innovators of rock 'n' roll guitar,
إنها واحدة من المبدعين لجيتار الروك أند رول،
and one of the first crossover artists from gospel to secular.
وواحدة من الفنانين الأوائل المنتقلين من الإنجيل إلى العلمانية.
She's an incredibly important figure,
إنها شخصية مهمة للغاية،
and I'm going to talk about her whenever I can.
وسأتحدث عنها وقتما أستطيع.
So these are a couple of her tunes.
إذاً هذه اثنين من ألحانها.
And don't worry -- you're going to get your chance to sing.
ولا تقلقوا فستحصلون على فرصتكم للغناء.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Sings) Look down, look down
(تغنى) انظر لأسفل، انظر لأسفل
that lonesome road
هذا الطريق وحيد
before you travel on.
قبل أن تسافر.
Look up, look up
انظر لأعلى، انظر لأعلى
and greet your maker,
وحيي خالقك،
for Gabriel blows his horn.
لينفخ جبريل في بوقه.
Weary totin' such a load,
ويحمل الضجر كحمل ثقيل،
goin' down that lonesome road.
وستهبط في هذا الطريق الوحيد.
Look down that lonesome road,
انظر لأسفل، فهذا الطريق وحيد
before you travel on.
قبل أن تسافر عليه.
Look down, look down
انظر لأسفل، انظر لأسفل
that lonesome road
فهذا طريقٌ وحيد
before you travel on.
قبل أن تسافر عليه.
Look up, look up
انظر لأعلى، انظر لأعلى
and greet your maker,
وحيي خالقك
for Gabriel blows his horn.
لينفخ جبريل في بوقه.
Weary totin' such a load,
ويحمل الضجر كحمل ثقيل،
goin' down that lonesome road.
وستهبط في هذا الطريق الوحيد.
Look down, look down, look down, look down
انظر لأسفل، انظر لأسفل، انظر لأسفل، انظر لأسفل
that lonesome road
فهذا طريقٌ وحيد
before you travel on.
قبل أن تسافر عليه.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear music in the air
أسمع موسيقى في الهواء
music in the air.
موسيقى في الهواء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear music in the air
أسمع موسيقى في الهواء
I hear music in the air.
أسمع موسيقى في الهواء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear music in the air
أسمع موسيقى في الهواء
music in the air
موسيقى في الهواء
and I really do believe
وأنا حقاً أعتقد
I really do believe
حقاً أعتقد
there's a Heaven somewhere.
أن هناك جنة في مكان ما.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear singin' in the air
أسمع غناءً في السماء
singin' in the air.
غناءً في السماء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear singin' in the air
أسمع غناءً في السماء
I hear singin' in the air.
أسمع غناءً في السماء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear singin' in the air
أسمع غناءً في السماء
singin' in the air
غناءً في السماء
and I really do believe
وأنا حقاً أعتقد
I really do believe
حقاً أعتقد
there's a Heaven somewhere.
أن هناك جنة في مكان ما.
(Speaks) All right now, guitar man!
(تتحدث) حسناً الآن، يا رجل الغيتار!
(Guitar music)
(موسيقى الغيتار)
That's Hubby Jenkins, y'all.
هذا هو هابى جينكينز يا رفاق.
(Sings) Up above my head
(تغني) فوق رأسي
up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear shoutin' in the air
أسمع صراخاً في الهواء
shoutin' in the air.
صراخاً في الهواء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear shoutin' in the air
أسمع صراخاً في الهواء
I hear shoutin' in the air.
أسمع صراخاً في الهواء.
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
I hear shoutin' in the air, that's right,
أسمع صراخاً في الهواء، هذا صحيح.
and I really do believe I really do believe
وأعتقد حقاً أعتقد حقاً
there's a heaven somewhere.
أن هناك جنة في مكان ما.
(Speaks) All right now, give me some of that bass.
(تتحدث) حسناً الآن، أعطني بعضاً من هذا الباص.
(Bass solo)
(عزف منفرد)
Yeah!
نعم!
Woo!
وو!
Jason Sypher on the bass.
جايسون سايفر على الباص.
Jamie Dick on those drums.
وجيمي ديك على تلك الطبول.
All right now,
حسناً الآن،
I'm running out of time.
إن الوقت يداهمني.
So it's time for y'all to sing.
لذا، فحان وقت غنائكم؟
This is the call-and-response.
فهو نداءٌ واستجابة.
I call, you respond.
أُنادي فتستجيبون.
There are so many songs like this, y'all know how it goes, don't you?
فهناك الكثير من الأغاني مثل هذا القبيل، وجميعكم يعرف كيف تبدو، أليس كذلك؟
You're going to sing along?
ستغنون معاً؟
I said, are you going to sing along?
قلت: ستغنون معاً؟
Audience members: Yes!
الجمهور: نعم.
Rhiannon Giddens: Here we go!
ريانون جيدنز: ها نحن ذا.
(Sings) Up above my head
(تُغنى) فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
الجمهور: فوق رأسي
RG: music in the air
(ر ج): موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air.
(ج م) : موسيقى في الهواء
RG: up above my head
(ر ج) : فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
(ج م) : فوق رأسي
RG: music in the air
(ر ج): موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air
(ج م): موسيقى في الهواء
RG: up above my head
(ر ج): فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
(ج م): فوق رأسي
RG: music in the air
(ر ج): موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air
(ج م): موسيقى في الهواء
RG: and I really do believe I really do believe
(ر ج): وأنا أعتقد حقاً، أنا أعتقد حقاً
there's a heaven somewhere.
أن هناك جنة في مكان ما.
One more time!
مرة أخرى!
Up above my head
فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
(ج م): فوق رأسي
RG: I hear music in the air
(ر ج): موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air.
(ج م): موسيقى في الهواء.
RG: Up above my head
(ر ج): فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
(ج م) : فوق رأسي
RG: I hear music in the air
(ر ج): أسمع موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air.
(ج م): موسيقى في الهواء.
RG: Up above my head
(ر ج): فوق رأسي
AM: up above my head
(ج م) : فوق رأسي
RG: I hear music in the air
(ر ج): أسمع موسيقى في الهواء
AM: music in the air
(ج م): موسيقى في الهواء
RG: and I really do believe I really do believe
(ر ج): وأعتقد حقاً، أعتقد حقاً
there's a heaven somewhere.
أن هناك جنة في مكان ما.
I said I really do believe I really do believe
فقد قلت أعتقد حقاً، أعتقد حقاً
Heaven somewhere.
جنة في مكان ما.
(Holds note)
(ثبات على النغمة)
(Applause and cheers)
(تصفيق وهتافات)
(Music ends)
(توقف الموسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)